<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The righteous mans death lamented. A sermon preached at St. Austins, London, Aug.23. 1662 at the funeral of that eminent servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. Simeon Ash late minister of the gospel there. By Edmund Calamy, B.D.</title>
            <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C262A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895693</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895693</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2346:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The righteous mans death lamented. A sermon preached at St. Austins, London, Aug.23. 1662 at the funeral of that eminent servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. Simeon Ash late minister of the gospel there. By Edmund Calamy, B.D.</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published as part of: The London-ministers legacy to their several congregations being a collection of farewel-sermons ... The second edition. (Wing L2905A).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:1"/>
            <p>THE Righteous Mans death LAMENTED. A SERMON PREACHED At St. <hi>Auſtins, London, Aug.</hi> 23. 1662, AT THE Funeral of that Eminent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. SIMEON ASH Late Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDMUND CALAMY,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <q>The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 112.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>AS the Words of Dying Men are remarkable, ſo the words ſpoken of at the Funerals of dead Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are moſt obſervable. Now Reader, this Sermon claims thy ſerious peruſal upon both theſe accompts; for as the Miniſter whoſe funeral he preached was dead, ſo the miniſter who preached it was civilly dying; for it was the laſt Sermon but one that the Reverend Author of this Sermon preach'd. Thus two Lights were put out together, although in a different manner; the one, his
<pb facs="tcp:153077:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153077:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:153077:5"/>light (as to us) is put under a clod of earth, and the other is put under a Buſhel.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay, this Sermon is in every word the ſame in publication, that it was in preaching; but this I ſhall ſay, I do not know, that there is one Cubit added to its Stature,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy</hi> Friend <hi>and</hi> Servant, M. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153077:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH LVII. Ver. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The righteous periſheth and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous are taken away from the evil to come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are here met this Evening, to perform the laſt Office of Love for an eminent and ancient Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, and excellent Miniſter of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh,</hi> one who hath formerly performed this Office for many other Miniſters; and now we are met to perform this Office for him; and it is not long before others will meet to perform the ſame office for us; ſo frail, ſo brittle, and ſo uncertain is the life of man.</p>
            <p>Now the Text that I have choſen, is ſuitable for this occaſion: For this Reverend Miniſter was firſt a righteous man; he was righteous in an Evangelical ſence, he was one that was juſtified, and ſanctified. Secondly, He was a mercifull man, both in an active and paſſive ſence; he was one that ſhewed mercy to the diſtreſſed Members of Jeſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153077:6"/>Chriſt, and he was one to whom God ſhewed mercy; this righteous and merciful man is now periſhed, as to his outward condition, not as to his everlaſting condition; but as to his outward bodily condition he is periſhed, and he is taken away; the word in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is very emphatical; <hi>merciful men, Colligu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur,</hi> are gathered; it is the ſame word that is uſed concerning <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt be gathered to thy Fathers, and go to thy grave in peace, and ſhalt not ſee the evil that I will bring upon this Nation.</hi> This godly and righteous man is now gathered, as ripe Corn in the Barn of Heaven; he is taken away from the evil that is to com, from the beholding that evil that is coming upon the ſinful World; he is taken away in mercy, that he may not be troubled with the troubles that are coming upon many; he is taken away from the evil to come.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee how ſuitable the Text is to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; there is only one particular that I deſire may prove unſuitable; for <hi>the righteous and merciful man</hi> in the Text, <hi>periſheth, and no man conſiders, nor layes it to heart;</hi> Theſe words are <hi>Verba Commentantis &amp; objurgantis;</hi> the words of the Prophet bemoaning the ſpiritual ſecurity of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> chiding and reproving them for their ſpiritual Lethargy: Now I deſire that this part may not prove ſuitable, but that all of you may lay to heart the death of this ancient, merciful, righteous man.</p>
            <p>The Obſervations from the words are theſe Six.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the righteous man muſt periſh as well as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the periſhing of a righteous man is nothing but his gathering to God, Chriſt, and the bleſſed company of Saints and Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That a righteous man as long as he liveth, is the preſervative of a Nation, and the ſupporter of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153077:6"/>the Chariots and Horſmen of a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The death of a righteous man is a Warning piece from Heaven, a Beacon ſet on fire to give notice of evil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>F fthly, <hi>That God doth on purpoſe take away righteous men, that they may not ſee the evil that is coming on a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>That it is a great and common ſin, not to conſider and lay to heart the death of a righteous man,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a common ſin, and therefore it is ſet down in the greateſt latitude; <hi>the righteous periſheth, and no man layes it to heart;</hi> that is, very few: <hi>And merciful men are taken away; no man conſidering!</hi> that is, very few.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, It is a great ſin; and therefore the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> in the former Chapter calls to all the Beaſts of the Field to devour, that is, all the Enemies of the Church to deſtroy the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they drank ſtrong drink, filling themſelves with merriment, and promiſed themſelves happy dayes, but did not conſider that <hi>the righteous were taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt, <hi>That the righteous periſh as well as the unrighteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is it that the righteous periſh? not in their ſoul, they cannot periſh ſo; nay, the truth is, they cannot periſh properly in their bodies; for the bodies of the Saints never totally and finally periſh; for the very duſt of the Saints in the grave, is precious in God's ſight, and they are aſleep in Jeſus, and by the power of Jeſus Chriſt they ſhall be raiſed again glorious bodies: Nothing periſheth of a righteous man by death totally, and finally, but ſin; and therefore the meaning of the word is, as <hi>Muſculus</hi> and <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr obſerve, <hi>perit,</hi> periſheth; that is, not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the truth of the thing, but according to the opinion of the world; and the proper language of this expreſſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153077:7"/>is this, <hi>The righteous periſh,</hi> that is, the righteous muſt dye, and go down to the houſe of rottenneſs, as well as others, and that upon a four-fold account,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe the righteous are included within the Statute of death as well as the unrighteous; <hi>ſtatutum eſt:</hi> Heb. 9.27. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to dye;</hi> the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as well as the unrighteous: Indeed it is true, Jeſus Chriſt hath taken away the hurt of death; but not death it ſelf; Jeſus Chriſt hath diſarmed death, made death like the Viper that faſtened upon <hi>Paul</hi>'s hand, but did not hurt him; he hath made it like the brazen Serpent that hath no ſting, but a healing power in it: Chriſt hath ſanctified death, conquered and ſweetned death; at preſent we are all under the Statute of death, but at laſt this Enemy ſhall be deſtroyed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, latter end.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The righteous conſiſt of periſhing principles as well as the unrighteous; the righteous are earthly veſſels, made of duſt; their foundation is in the duſt; their lives are a vapour as well as the lives of the unrighteous.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, The righteous muſt dye as well as others, becauſe they have a body of ſin that they carry about with them; for there is no man ſo wiſe, that lives and ſins not, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. Wherefore there is that which deſerves death in a righteous man.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and eſpecially, The righteous muſt periſh upon a peculiar account; <hi>For if we had hope only in this life</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we are of all men moſt miſerable,</hi> and therefore they muſt periſh to keep them from periſhing, they muſt ſay as <hi>Themiſtocles, Periiſſem niſi periiſſem;</hi> they muſt dye, that they may reſt from their labour; for here is not our reſt, <hi>Micah</hi> 2.10. There remaineth a reſt for the people of God; there is no reſt in this World; the word <hi>quies</hi> wants the plural number.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, The righteous muſt dye, that they may have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153077:7"/>their reward, their Crown of glory that God hath laid up for them; they muſt firſt fight the good ſight, and finiſh their courſe, and then they ſhall receive a Crown of glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. They muſt dye, that they may be free from ſin; for they ſhal never put off the body of ſin, till they put off the body of fleſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. They muſt die, that mortality may be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up of life, that corruption may put on incorruption.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. They muſt dye, that they may be perfect in Grace.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They muſt die, that they may ſee God face to face, and be for ever with the Lord, which they cannot do till they dye; therefore bleſſed be God that the r gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous muſt periſh. If a man ſhould bring news to a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, that he ſhould always live on Earth, always be young, rich and healthful, it would be unwelcom news; for while we are in the body, we are abſent from the Lord, and ſubject to ſin; and therefore when <hi>Peter</hi> asked Chriſt what ſhould be done with <hi>John,</hi> Chriſt tells him, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what's that to thee?</hi> from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there went a report abroad that <hi>John</hi> ſhould not die, <hi>John</hi> 21.32. Now the Apoſtle himſelf was much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with this report, and look't upon it as a great affliction that he ſhould not die, and therefore he himſelf confutes it; <hi>But yet Jeſus</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſaid not that he ſhould not dye;</hi> as if he had ſaid, God forbid that I ſhould not die.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the Application of this point, give me leave to ſpeak ſomething to the ſecond point, and ſo I ſhal apply them both together.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Doctrine is this, <hi>That the periſhing of a righteous man, is nothing but a gathering of him to God, Chriſt, and the bleſſed Society of Saints and Angels in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is contained in the ſecond expreſſion, <hi>Merciful men are taken away;</hi> the word in the Hebrew is <hi>colliguntu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> they are gathered; it is exegetical of the former; they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153077:8"/>did not periſh, but they are gathered to God and Chriſt; there is a great deal of excellency, &amp; a magazine of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this expreſſion, <hi>they are gathered;</hi> It implies two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the righteous are in a ſcattered condition while they are in this World, and that three ways:</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are ſcattered among the wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly of the World, as Sheep among Wolves, as Lambs among Lions, rent and torn in pieces, forced to wander up and down in ſheep-skins and Goat skins.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The righteous are ſcattered in the world one from another, and that two ways: 1. They are ſcattered by their different habitations; for the godly are forced to ſeparate one from another, as <hi>Lot</hi> from <hi>Abraham.</hi> 2. They are ſcattered one from another by the cruel perſecution of wicked men; and therefore you read <hi>Acts</hi> 8. that at that time when there was a perſecution againſt the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that <hi>they were all ſcattered abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly, The godly are ſcattered in this life from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence of God in Heaven; indeed they are never ſattered from the gracious preſence of God, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are ſcattered from the comforting preſence of God; and as long as we live in this World, we ſhall be ſcattered from the glorious preſence of God; for while we are in the body, we are abſent from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This implyes a bringing of God's people out of this ſcattered condition; it is a gathering of the righteous out of this world into another, from a ſinfull perſecuted world, into a ſinles glorious world, from diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of dwellings on earth, to dwell altogether in one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; it is a gathering out of the reach of men and divels: a gathering them not only to the gracious, but to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence of God and Chriſt, and to the ſouls of juſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153077:8"/>men made perfect, and to the general aſſembly of the firſt born, and to the city of the living God, the heavenly <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where they ſhall live together, never to be ſcattered again. To underſtand this the better, let me offer 3 things to you, ſhewing you that the godly are gathered to God 3 wayes: In this life, at death, and at the day of judgment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the righteous are gathered to God in this life, and that is at their firſt converſion; for by nature we are all aliens and ſtrangers to God; ſcattered from any union or communion with God: not only ſcattered from the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but from the gracious preſence of God. God made man at firſt to enjoy communion with himſelf, but <hi>Adam</hi> loſt this by his ſin, and now we are all <hi>Cains,</hi> and Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, ſcattered from the love of God, and from union and communion with God; but when God converts any of the elect, he gathers them home to himſelf; for converſion is nothing but God's gathering them to himſelf in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> that were ſcattered from him in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was a root of ſcattering, a root of ſeparation from God; but the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was a root of union and conjunction. Chriſt is the head, and all the elect are all gathered together in him, 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 10. that he might gather together in one all things in Chriſt; ſo that converſion is nothing but a gathering of the elect of God to Chriſt by faith, and a gathering to one another by love and charity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods people are gathered at death; here they are gathered to Chriſt by grace, but at death they are gathered to Chriſt in glory, here they are gathered to God by hope, but at death by fruition; here Chriſt is gathered to us, he comes down, and dwells with us; but at death we ſhall be gathered to him, we ſhall go up, and be joynd with him. There's a great deal of difference between <hi>eſſe cum Chriſte,</hi> and <hi>eſſe in Chriſto; eſſe cum Chriſto,</hi> to be one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153077:9"/>with Chriſt is a Chriſtians great ſecurity; but <hi>eſſe in Chriſto,</hi> to be one in Chriſt, it is a Chriſtians great felicity: In this life we are gathered to God by faith, but at death by viſion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we ſhall be gathered to God at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it is called the day of the gathering of the Saints to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; A day when all the Saints that are, have been, or ſhall be, ſhall all be gathered together. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you brethren, by the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and by our gathering together unto him at the great day; At the day of judgement we ſhall all be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and ſhall be all taken up to heaven, I mean all the righteous, and be ever with the Lord; and ſo much for the opening of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>But here it may be objected; Are not the unrighteous gathered by death as well as the righteous?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, it is true, the unrighteous are ſcattered in this life, and gathered by death as well as the righteous; but with a great deal of difference.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the wicked are ſcattered in this life, but they are ſcattered from God; but the godly are ſcattered for God and for a good conſcience many times, as they as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were ſcattered: The godly are ſcattered from the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence of God in heaven; but the wicked are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the gracious preſence of God on earth. Again the ſcattering of the wicked is a curſe to them, and it is threatned as a curſe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.32. I will ſcatter you among the heathen, and draw out my ſword after you; and wherever the wicked come, in what part ſoever of the world the wicked are ſcattered, they bring the curſe of God with them, and they bring the judgments of God on Towns or Cities where they are, as plauge, famine, and ſword, and all miſeries. But the godly, when they are ſcattered, they are ſcattered as a bleſſing; into what
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153077:9"/>Country or Town ſoever they come, they come as a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, they come like a ſhip laden with corn, to a Town ready to periſh with famine; they come as a bleſſing four ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by their prayers, to pray down a bleſſing on the place where they come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they come as a bleſſing by their holy life and converſation, that is a loadſtone to draw others to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they come as a bleſſing by their holy adviſe and counſel that they give to the place where they come.</p>
            <p>Nay fourthly, their very preſence is a bleſſing; as long as <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom, Sodom</hi> could not be deſtroyed; ſo long as <hi>Paul</hi> was in the ſhip, the three hundred could not be drown'd. So that the godly come as a bleſſing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are ſcattered; but the wicked are as chaffe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the wind, and they are ſcattered as the duſt of the earth: You know when the duſt is ſcattered, it gets into mens eyes and blinds them, and falls upon their cloaths and fullies and defiles them; ſo the wicked, where-ever they are ſcattered, they defile the place where they are ſcattered. The godly are as planets, that wander and move from one part of heaven to another, carrying light to the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the wicked are ſcattered whiſe they live, ſo when they dye, they are gathered, it is true; but how? not to God, and Chriſt, and his Angels, but they are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to the divel, and his Angels, and to damned ſpirits: not as bundles of wheat into the barn of heaven, but as bundles of tares to be burned for ever in everlaſting fire.</p>
            <p>Now, if the righteous periſh as well as others, and if their periſhing be nothing but a gathering to God and Chriſt; then,</p>
            <p>Firſt, learn hence the preciouſneſs of every righteous man; the great God will not gather things of no value;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153077:10"/>great men do not uſe to gather chaffe and ſtraw; and therefore, when God ſaith of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> I will gather thee to thy Fathers, it was a ſign he was a precious pearl worth the gathering, and of a high value and account in the ſight of God: and ſo is every true child of God; right dear and precious are they in the ſight of God, both living and dying; they are bought with a great price: not with gold and ſilver, and other corruptible things, but they are bought with the precious blood of the Son of God: They are as precious to God as the apple of his eye; ſo precious that be hath given Chriſt for them and to them: ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that he called them his Jewels, his peculiar treaſure, <hi>Jedidiahs,</hi> and therefore God will not ſuffer them to periſh, but gather them to himſelf before the evil day come, as the husbandman gathers in the corn before the beaſts go out into the field.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Learn here what reaſon we have to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in the death of a righteous man or woman, becauſe their death is not a periſhing, but a gathering to God and Chriſt, and the ſociety of Saints and Angels. The death of a righteous man is no more then if a Merchant that hath abundance of Jewels in a far country, ſhould ſend for them home. Why death to a righteous man is nothing but Gods ſending for his Jewels home. Such a phraſe there is in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. In the day that I make up my Jewels, they ſhall be mine. In this life they are imperfect Jewels; they are like gold in the oar, mingled with a great deal of droſſe; and death is nothing but a perfecting of theſe Jewels; death is nothing more; and God doth nothing by death, but as a gold-finder gather up all his ends of gold and ſilver: It is nothing but juſt as if a Father ſhould ſend for his Son home that had been a long while abſent from him to his own Houſe; it is a carrying us to our Father's houſe: And therefore let us be comforted when
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153077:10"/>our righteous Friends dye; though their death be matter of ſorrow to us, in regard of the loſs that we ſuſtain by their death; and becauſe their death is a Warning piece of evil to come; yet in regard of them we have no cauſe to mourn. I ſpeak this to thoſe that are related to the righteous when they dye: Did you ever hear of a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman that mourned for the carrying of his Corn into the Barn? or a Jeweller mourn for making up of his Jewels? Let us mourn rather that we are left ſcattered among the wicked of the earth, and from the glorious preſence of God and Chriſt; and let us mourn for thoſe that are ſcattered from Chriſt, and from grace; and for thoſe that whileſt they live, are ſcattered, and when they dye, are gathered to the Devil and his Angels: Let us not mourn for thoſe that dye in Chriſt, but let us mourn for thoſe that live out of Chriſt; let us not mourn over the body that the ſoul hath left, but let us mourn over the ſoul that God hath left.</p>
            <p>The third Uſe is of Conſolation to all the people of God in reference to evil times that are coming upon us, or to the evil of times. Whatever befalls a Child of God in this life, though he be ſcattered by wicked men, from <hi>England</hi> into other Forreign Countreys, though he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and down in Deſarts and Wilderneſſes, though he be ſcattered from houſe to priſon, yet there will be a gathering time ſhortly, there will a time come when all the Saints ſhall be gathered to Chriſt, and to one another, never to part any more. The death of Gods people is not a periſhing, but a gathering: comfort your ſelves therefore with theſe words, againſt the fear of death: look upon death as a gathering, as a gathering to Chriſt: You are here as <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons Den, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon: yet there will come a gathering, and if you dye in a good cauſe, you ſhall not periſh, but be gathered to Chriſt, and to his Saints and Angels.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153077:11"/>
            <p> But you will ſay, <hi>If I were ſure when I dye, that I ſhould be gathered to Chriſt, to live for ever with him, this would be matter of great conſolation to me, but you told me, the wicked are gathered by death as well as the godly, how ſhall I know whether (when I come todye) I ſhall be gathered to the Devil and his Angels, or to Chriſt and his Angele? How ſhall</hi> I <hi>know whether</hi> I <hi>ſhall be gathered at death as a bundle of tares to be burned in Hell, or as a bundle of wheat to be carried up into the Burn of Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, You may know it by four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you are righteous, then you ſhall be gathered to Chriſt at death, <hi>for the righteous ſhall go into everlaſting life?</hi> Heaven is entailed upon righteous men by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I mean the imputed righteouſneſs, and the imparted righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt; I wave the explication of them, becauſe time will not give leave. <hi>Know you not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that no unrighteous man ſhall inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God?</hi> Damnation is entailed upon unrighteous men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you are merciful, the merciful man ſhall be gathered to Chriſt, if you are one that is full of bowels of compaſſion to the diſtreſſed Members of Jeſus Chriſt, for Chriſt hath ſaid it, <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mercy.</hi> Now if you are hard hearted, covetous, world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded, remember that Text, <hi>He ſhall have judgement without mercy, that ſhews no mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, He that is gathered to the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> by faith in this world, ſhall certainly be gathered unto Chriſt by viſion in the other world, Chriſt Ieſus will ſave all his members, and you muſt know, that Faith is a tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Grace, it is not onely a heart purifying, but a world-overcoming grace, it takes a man out of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> and put's him into the new <hi>Adam;</hi> it takes a man out of the root of ſcattering, and puts him into the root of union
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153077:11"/>and conjunction: Wherefore you that are now joined to Chriſt by faith here, ſhall be joined to Chriſt in glory hereafter: But now you that are Vagabonds, <hi>Cains</hi> and Aliens from the life of God, and from the life of Grace: You that are wooden Members wooden Legs in Chriſts body, that have no real conjunction with Chriſt, you ſhal not be gathered to him in glory.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If you are gathered here to the Saints by love, then you ſhall be gathered to the Saints in Heaven, and to the everlaſting enjoyment of God with them to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Conſider this, Every man ſhall be gathered (when he dies) to thoſe whom he delights, and chooſeth to keep company with while he lives in this world: If you are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to the wicked in love and affection here, you ſhall be gathered to them at death in Hell and deſtruction, for it's pity companions ſhould be parted: Wheat muſt to Wheat, and Tares to Tares, for Wheat and Tares ſhall not be bound together at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>The laſt uſe is of Exhortation: It the righteous muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and if their death be nothing but a gathering, then take this threefold Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us labour to make the beſt uſe we can of our godly friends and Miniſters before they are gathered, let us do as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did, he was told that his Maſter <hi>Elijah</hi> was to be taken up to Heaven, and therefore he would never leave him till he had got the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> doubled upon him: If <hi>Eliſha</hi> had not thought that <hi>Elijah</hi> would have been taken up that day, he would never have followed him ſo punctually and inſeparably as he did. O beloved, did you believe that text, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.5. of which we have often had experience, <hi>your fathers, where are they; and the Prophets, do they live for ever?</hi> Indeed if they did live for ever, we might get good from them when we pleaſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſure never to loſe them; but they live not for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153077:12"/>ever, but muſt periſh, and be taken up to heaven: And therefore whilſt we have them, let us make what uſe we can of them, before they be taken away from us. It is a great fault among the people of God, that they make no more uſe of their godly Friends and Miniſters. I have known many that have godly Relations that have died, that it hath been the greateſt burthen on their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they got no more good by thoſe godly Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons while they lived. Many of us deal with our Miniſters as we do with a ſtrange ſight that is to be ſeen near our doors; we are not much ſolicitous when we ſee it. But a ſtranger that comes from a far Countrey, is curious, and very carefull preſently to ſee it. So do we in this City e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, I have had experience of it by being here many yeares; ſtrangers that come out of the Countrey, many times get that good by a Miniſter, that his own people do not, becauſe they think their Miniſter is continually with them: But a ſtranger knows he is there but for a day, and he hears ſo, that he carries Chriſt home with him, and a great deal of conſolation alſo. Beloved, this is a great fault; I beſeech you remember, the righteous muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; let us therefore do with them as we do with Books that are borrowed; if a man borrows a Book, he knows he muſt keep it but for a day or two, and therefore he will be ſure to read it over; whereas if the Book be a mans own, he layes it aſide, becauſe he knows he can read it at any time. Remember, your Miniſters are but lent you, they are not your own, and you know not but God may take your <hi>Elijahs</hi> from you this night: Therefore make what uſe you can of them, while you have them.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Muſt the righteous be taken away? Then let the righteous make conſcience of doing what good they can before they are taken away. Beloved, if it were poſſible for the godly to grieve in Heaven, this would be their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153077:12"/>greateſt ſorrow, that they have done God no more ſervice here upon Earth. Be wiſe for God, O ye righteous; do as old men do that have rich places and offices; they labour to buy the reverſion of their places for their children: ſo muſt you to whom God hath given great gifts and graces, labour to propagate your gifts and graces, that there may be no loſs by your death. Obſerve the care of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the aged in his exhortations to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.5, 6. <hi>Watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, do the work of an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, make full proof of thy Miniſtry:</hi> why ſo? <hi>for I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand:</hi> and therefore work thou, ſee that thou endure affliction, preach the Goſpel as becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel, that there may be no loſs by my departure: ſo in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>The things that thou haſt heard of me among many witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithful men that ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> Hath God committed any thing to you? a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Learning or grace? commit it to young Miniſters, that they may commit it to others, that ſo there may be a ſucceſſion of gifts and graces: Do as Phyſicians do, that labour to communicate their skil to their Children, and to others: ſo ſhould we, that ſo there may be a ſucceſſion of godly ones, that godlineſs may be entailed upon us and our Relations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, let us all labour to be ſuch, that when we die, when we come to be gathered, we may be gathered to Chriſt, and his Angels; and not to the Divel, and his Angels. And for that purpoſe, let us labour to be merciful and righteous, and let us be gathered to Chriſt by faith, and to one another by love and dear affection: and then we ſhall be gathered at the great day to Chriſt, and the bleſſed company of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are Four Obſervations yet behind, but I muſt waye them at this time.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153077:13"/>
            <p> I have now another Sermon to preach, and I cannot without injury to you that are alive, and without wrong to the memory of my dearly beloved brother, but ſpeak ſomthing of him at whoſe funeral we are met this evening, no ſo much for his commendation, he needs it not, but for our imitation: It is pitty, great pitty ſomthing ſhould not be ſaid, that this reverend Miniſter though dead, may yet preach this night; and I have ſo much to ſay of him, that I know not where to begin; and when I have begun, I hardly know how to make an end: I muſt confeſs, the little time allotted me for the providing for this ſolemn work, and the neceſſary avocations in this little time, have hindered me from informing my ſelf about his breeding and manner of education at <hi>Emanuel Colledge</hi> under Mr. <hi>Stooker,</hi> and his excellent carriage and converſe with Mr. <hi>Hild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſam,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> Mr. <hi>Langley,</hi> and other Miniſters, famous in their generations; and the many preſſures and hardſhips that he ſuffered in thoſe parts and times, for the keeping of his conſcience pure from that which he counted ſin; and therefore I muſt draw a vail over that part of his life, and confine my difcourſe only to the time ſince his coming to live with us in <hi>London,</hi> which is about the ſpace of twenty two, or three and twenty years; all which time, I have had the happineſs to be intimately acquainted with him, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that I can freely and clearly profeſs, and that with a ſad heart, that I, and many others, have loſt a real, wiſe, and godly friend, brother, and fellow-labourer in the Lord; the Church hath loſt an eminent member, and choice pillar: and this City hath loſt an ancient, faithful, and painful Miniſter; who by his prayers and holy life, did ſeek to keep off the judgments of God from faling upon us; and the leſs ſenſible the City is of this loſs, the greater is the loſs. I fear we may too truly repeat the words in the Text, <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man lay it to heart; and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153077:13"/>merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous are taken away from the evil to come.</hi> I have read of <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> and by chance met with the ſame in the life of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that when they came to any City or Town, and heard of the death of any godly man, though never ſo poor, they would both of them mourn exceedingly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great loſs that place had by the death of that godly man, and becauſe it was a warning-piece from God of evil approaching But we have had many godly men, and godly Miniſters, taken away of late, and yet I fear me, but few lay it to heart; and therefore as I ſaid, the loſs is the greater to this City, becauſe it is ſo little ſenſible of it. It is a great loſs alſo to his Relations; his wife hath loſt a dear and loving husband, his ſiſter a dear brother, his Pariſh and Congregation a faithful Paſtour.</p>
            <p>The miniſterial Excellencies of many Miniſters were collected &amp; concentred in one <hi>Simeon Aſh,</hi> he was a <hi>Bezaleel</hi> in Gods Tabernacle, a Maſter-builder, and old Diſciple, a <hi>Polycarpe,</hi> a Chriſtian of long ſtanding in the School of Chriſt, a burning and a ſhining light, one whom many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and other good Chriſtians called Father, inſomuch that it was a common Proverb in this City, Father <hi>Aſh;</hi> and I believe, many experimentaly lament over him, as the King did over the Propet <hi>Eliſha; My Father, my father, the chariots of Iſrael, and the horſmen thereof!</hi> For he lived deſired, and died lamented, not only in the city, but I believ in very many places in the Country where he was known. But more particularly, there were twelve excellencies that I obſerved in this reverend Miniſter, and my dear Brother, that were as twelve jewels or precious pearls in that crown with which God had crowned him: I ſhall name them for your imitation and benefit; he needs them not, for he is above our Eulogy.</p>
            <p>The firſt and chief Jewel that I did beautifie and adorn
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153077:14"/>this our brother, was his ſincerity and uprightnes of heart; which indeed is not a ſingle grace, but the ſoul of all grace, and the interlineary that muſt run through all grace; for what is faith if it be not unfained? what will love to God profit you if it be not without diſſimulation? what is repentance worth if it be not in truth? as the body without the ſoul is a rotten carkaſs, ſo is all grace without ſincerity; this is the ſoul of all grace, this is the girdle of truth. Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is that which girts all our ſpiritual armour together and makes them uſeful; what advantage is it to have the breaſtplate of righteouſneſs, the ſhield of faith, the helmet of hope, if they be but painted things? it is the girdle of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity that makes all the other parts of our armour uſeful. Now this excellent grace of ſincerity was eminent in this our dear brother; he was a true <hi>Nathanael,</hi> in whom there was no guile; I mean, no allowed hypocriſie; and this was that which carried him through the pangs of death with a great deal of comfort; for he was able to ſay with <hi>Hezekiah, Remember, O Lord, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart.</hi> He could ſay with <hi>Paul, This is my rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, the teſtimony of my conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, I have had my converſation in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Another Jewel was his humility; this is a grace that he was cloathed withal, and it is a rare grace; for God dwells with the humble; he reſiſts the proud, but he gives grace to the humble. This Reverend Miniſter was low in his own eyes, and therefore very high in Gods eyes; he had a mean eſteem of himſelf, and therefore he was in high eſteem with God. He was as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of himſelf, leſs then the leaſt of God's mercies, and therefore he was made partaker of the beſt of God's mercies. He was like an ear of corn, full of fruit, bowing down in thankfulneſs to God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, another Jewel was the fruitfulneſs, of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153077:14"/>diſcourſe; for it may be ſaid of him, as it was of Chriſt, he went about doing good; wherever he went, he ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his goodneſs; this all that knew him, know to be true. He was full of good diſcourſe wherever he came; when I was with him in his ſickneſs, he took occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain much, and not without juſt cauſe; (God grant his complaint may make impreſſion upon our hearts) he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that it was a great fault among Miniſters, that when they met together, they diſcourſed no more of Chriſt, of heaven, and of the concernments of the other world; and profeſſed, that if God ſhould reſtore him, he would be more careful in his diſcourſe; and more fruitful then ever yet he had been.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, another Jewel that beautified this righteous man, was his mercifulneſs; He was a merciful man, whic he manifeſted not only in his charity to the members of Jeſus Chriſt, but in his frequent viſiting of ſick perſons, and perſons that needed his ſpiritual phyſick. I know not any Miniſter in the City more careful in viſiting the ſick then he was.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, another Jewel was his prudence and ſpiritual wiſdome; he was not only a pious and godly, but a wiſe and prudent miniſter; that had zeal for God, but knew how to mingle his zeal with diſcretion; diſcretion indeed without zeal is nothing but carnal policy; but zeal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcretion, is nothing but frantick fury; diſcretion without zeal will quickly eat out the heart of religion, and eat religion out of the heart-Zeal without diſcretion, is not a coal from the Altar, but a coal kindled by the wild fire of paſſion, that is able to ſet a Nation on fire; but this reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſter had zeal ſweetly tempered with diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Another Jewel was his patience; God was pleaſed to exerciſe him with long and great afflictions by reaſon of the Gout, that did often, eſpecially of late years
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153077:15"/>affix him to his bed, and afflict him with great pain; but God was pleaſed to put his everlaſting Arms underneath him, ſupporting him under all his pains, and giving him a great meaſure of patience, inſomuch that in patience he did poſſeſs his ſoul, and patience had its perfect work in him.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Jewel was his high valuation of Ieſus Chriſt; a written copy for us to follow, and for you his people alſo. Being with him in his laſt ſickneſs, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted me and other Miniſters with him to preach much of Ieſus Chriſt, and to ſpeak to him of Ieſus Chriſt; and he ſaid, <hi>when I conſider my beſt duties, I ſink, I dye, I deſpair; but when</hi> I <hi>think of Chriſt,</hi> I <hi>have enough, he is all; and in all.</hi> I think theſe were his very words. <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to know nothing but Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified: I account all things dung and droſs, that</hi> I <hi>may be found in Chriſt:</hi> To this effect he ſpake in the morning before the evening in which he died, ſpeaking much of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Another jewel was his diligence in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; in the time of his health he was a painful, laborious Preacher; one that did not Preach to tickle the ear, but to wound the heart; not to pleaſe, but to profit; not ſeeking the applauſe of the people, but the ſalvation of their ſouls: This all know to be true.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, Another Jewel that did beautifie and adorn this Reverend Miniſter, was his excellent gift in Prayer; and herein he was very eminent, and did exceed many, nay I may ſay moſt of his Brethren: As <hi>Apollos</hi> was mighty in the ſcriptures, ſo was he (as you all know) mighty in Prayer; he was a <hi>Iacob,</hi> very skilful in wreſtling with God, like <hi>Moſes</hi> he often ſtood in the gap, and at moſt Faſts in the time of his health, he was the Miniſter that was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to conclude with Prayer; and this heightens the loſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153077:15"/>that we ſuſtain by the death of this godly Miniſter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have loſt the benefit of his Prayers, which is an invaluable loſs; for though I doubt not but he prays in Heaven for the Church in general, yet I believe he prays not for any in particular, as not knowing what our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is; <hi>For Abraham knows us not;</hi> for the Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven know not what is done upon earth. The loſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the greater, becauſe we have loſt not onely a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but a praying Miniſter: And give me leave to add, that this excellency in this Miniſter, is ſufficient to prove, 1. That there is a gift of prayer, which ſome againſt al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon do deny. 2. That conceived prayers when uttered by one that hath the gift of prayer, are not in vain <hi>Tautologies,</hi> or empty repetitions, and a rate of nonſence asſome unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge men with; but they are the breathings of God's Spirit, that pierce not onely into the ears and hearts of the hearers, but into the ears and heart of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, The next jewel was, He had great acquaintance and communion with God; for he was of a long ſtanding in the School of Chriſt, and a good Proficient in that School. Much acquaintance he had with God he was often in the Mount with God, and came down with his face ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, though he in his modeſty did not ſee it; and when he came to dye, he was able to ſay as <hi>Dr. Preſton</hi> did when he lay a dying, I <hi>ſhall change my place, but not my company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Another jewel was, his comfortable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of this world, dying with a great deal of calmneſs and ſerenity upon his Conſcience; The morning before he dyed, <hi>I heard him</hi> ſay theſe words, <hi>It is one thing to ſpeak of Chriſt, and of Heaven, and another thing to feel the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Chriſt and of Heaven, as</hi> I <hi>do;</hi> calpping his hand on his breaſt. Another time I heard him ſay, <hi>The comforts of a holy life are real, ſoul-ſupporting, and that he felt the reality of thoſe comforts, and that by him we might know it was not in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153077:16"/>vain to ſerve God.</hi> And I cannot forget this ſpeech the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before he died, I <hi>am a little ſtraitned, but</hi> I <hi>care no more for my lifs, then</hi> I <hi>do for this fill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p:</hi> That which was ſaid of old <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luk. 2. may be ſaid of this Reverend mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <hi>Mr Simeon Aſh,</hi> who was a <hi>Simeon,</hi> a juſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout man, an old Servant of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> one that waited for the conſolation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> one that dyed, though not with Chriſt in his bodily Arms, yet with Chriſt in the Arms of his Faith; and when he died, could ſay as it is there, <hi>Now Lord, letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation.</hi> Laſtly, Another Jewel was his conſtancy and perſeverance; he was not a Reed ſhaken with every wind, but as firm as a Rock: an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable pillar in God's Houſe; he was unchangeable in changeable times; in Religion he was a houſe built on a Rock, not on the Sand; and as he lived, ſo he dyed holily, even as the ancient Patriarks that dyed in the Faith, and endured faithfully unto the death.</p>
            <p>Now this excellent Miniſter of Chriſt thus beautified with theſe jewels, is now periſhed as to his outward man, gathered to God, to Chriſt, and the bleſſed company of Saints and Angels. The application that I ſhall make of this Diſcourſe, is this:
<list>
                  <item>1. To us Miniſters.</item>
                  <item>2. To you of this Pariſh and Congregation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to us Miniſters. God hath of late years taken to himſelf many famous men: Seven of the Lecturers of <hi>Cornhill</hi> are dead, <hi>Mr. Burroughs, Dr. Bolton, Mr. Sedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Mr. Whitaker, Mr. Cranford, Mr. Vines,</hi> and now <hi>Mr. Aſh.</hi> I might name many other excellent Miniſters that are dead, as <hi>Dr. Gouge, Mr. Walker, Mr. Gataker, Mr. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, Mr. Robinſon,</hi> and lately <hi>Mr. Cook,</hi> with many more: Now all theſe are warning-pieces from Heaven of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments approaching; <hi>For the righteons periſh, and no man
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153077:16"/>lays it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous are taken away from the evil to come.</hi> Thus <hi>Methuſelah</hi> dyed a year before the Flood: Now <hi>Methuſelah</hi> in <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>a miſſenger of death.</hi> Thus <hi>Auſtin</hi> dyed a little before <hi>Hippo</hi> was taken; and <hi>Pareus</hi> a little before <hi>Hiddleburg</hi> was taken, and <hi>Luther</hi> a little before the Wars in <hi>Germany</hi> began. The death of the godly is like the ſeparating of the Iſraelites from the tents of <hi>Corah</hi> and his company; like the taking of <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodome.</hi> When the Iſraelites departed from <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, the earth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up; and when <hi>Lot</hi> departed out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> God rained down fire and brimſtone upon them. Let the thoughts of theſe things cauſe us to provide our Arks, to get our <hi>Zoar</hi>'s. Let it teach young <hi>Samuel's</hi> to riſe up in the room of old <hi>Ely's;</hi> young <hi>Eliſha's,</hi> in the room of old <hi>Elijah's,</hi> and young <hi>Timothy's;</hi> in the room of <hi>Paul</hi> the aged; that there may be a ſucceſſion of Goſpel Miniſters to hold forth the word of life to this Nation. And let us labour to be inheritours of theſe twelve Exellencies, that beautified this our reverend Brother.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let me ſpeak a few words to you of this Pariſh, the Auditors of this worthy Miniſter. There is ſcarce one man of a hundred, that underſtands the tye and obligation that is betwixt a Miniſter and his people. O the love and affection that ought to be betwixt them! <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that they could a pluckt out their eyes for him if need were. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tells us, that when <hi>Miletius</hi> was taken away by death from his people, their heart ſunk with ſorrow; and ſuch love had they to him, that they called all their children by his name, and got his picture engraven on their rings. And I have read of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that when he was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from his people, there was not a corner in the City, but was full of people weeping and lamenting. The loſs of a godly Miniſter, is a publick loſs, and therefore there ought to be publick mourning; it is a ſoul loſs, and therefore, methinks, every one of you ſhould weep and mourn; you have loſt your common father, your ſpiritual ſhepherd; you have loſt your eyes, your guide; and indeed it is you that are his flock that muſt commend your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by practiſing that which he preached; ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Do we again begin to commend our ſelves, or need we as ſome others, Epiſtles of commendations to you, or letters of commendations from you? Ye are our Epiſtle written in our hearts, known and read of all men.</hi> As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, Do we need letters of commendation? is it neceſſary that we ſhould ſpend time in commending our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry? you are our letters of commendation; your holineſs and
<pb facs="tcp:153077:17"/>piety commends a Miniſter above all other things. As when a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comes into an Orchard or Vineyard, ſaid <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and ſees every thing skilfully handled, and neatly trimmed, he need not ſpend time in commending the Vine-dreſſer, or Carpenter; the work it ſelf commends them. So ought it to be among you; when we preach the Funeral Sermons of Miniſters, we muſt look into his Pariſh or Congregation, and ſee what letters of commendation there are; whither the proficiency of the Auditors commend their Miniſters. I grant, it is not always true God doth not always give ſucceſs to a godly Miniſter; but the worſt is yours; I had almoſt ſaid the curſe is yours; but I will ſpeak modeſtly, the worſt is yours. Tel me how many of you are able to ſay, I bleſs God that ever ſuch a Miniſter was ſent among us; bleſſed be God that ever we heard him preach, what ſeal of his Miniſtry is there here among you? he was in another, and another place in this City; it may be here are people from all places that have been his Auditors; what ſeal of his miniſtry is there now to be found among you? how many ſouls hath he pluckt out of the ſnares of the devil? how many of you have gone away weeping from a Sermon, knocking your breaſts, and pricked at the hearts for ſin, crying out; <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> your tears and mourning for ſin; theſe are the auditors that commend your miniſters. Go home now, and think with your ſelvs, What can I remember of all the Sermons that I have heard from Mr. <hi>Aſh?</hi> and give me leave to tell you, wo be to you, if as your miniſter be dead, ſo all the Sermons that he made dye with him: For as <hi>Abel</hi> being dead, yet ſpeaketh; ſo ſhall the Sermons of this worthy Miniſter, at the great day, ſpeak for you, or againſt you; for they are ſpiritual talents that God hath betruſted you with, and you muſt be accountable; both he and you ſhall appear before the Tribunal of God; your Miniſter ſhall be examined, how he can free himſelf from the guilt of ſoul blood; and you ſhall be examined, what fruit you have brought forth, anſwerable to the means that you have enjoyed; and if it appear that you have been unprofitable and unfruitful Hearers, Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Caſt the unprofitable ſervant into utter darkneſs.</hi> But I hope better things of you, and things that accompany ſalvation. Whatever was good in this reverend Miniſter, let it live in you; and though he be dead, yet let not his Sermons that he preached dye with you, but let them be in you, that at the great day, when he and you appear before God, he may be able to ſay, <hi>Here am I, and the Children that thou haſt given me.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153077:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
